okay let's do some practice regarding
enthalpy of combustion so the question
asks how much heat is released upon the
combustion of 1.00 litres of isooctane
and that has the formula C8H18. now in
order to answer this question we will
need to know that the density of
isooctane is zero point six nine two
grams per milliliter and we also need to
know that the Delta H of combustion for
iso-octane is negative 5461 kilojoules
per mole so this is all the data you
need go ahead and give this a try.
so let's start out with our one point
zero zero liters of isooctane what are
we gonna do first well we know we're
gonna do some kind of stoichiometry so
we're gonna want to try to get two moles
so how do we do this well we've got
liters and our density was in grams per
milliliter so we're gonna need in
milliliters so let's just convert this
into milliliters first we've got one
point zero zero liters times a thousand
and since we can only have three sig
figs that is going to be one point zero
zero times 10 to the 3 milliliters. now
as we said we have that density so we
can convert to grams one point zero zero
times 10 to the 3 milliliters times zero
point six nine two grams per milliliter
milliliters will cancel and we'll get
692 grams so now that we have a mass of
isooctane we want to use that mass to
get moles because that way we can use
the Delta H of combustion that we were
given so 692 grams times 1 mol / 114
grams that's what we get just by adding
up all the carbon and hydrogen atoms
that is going to give us six
point zero seven moles so we have six
point zero seven moles of isooctane in
that one liter of isooctane and then
lastly we can use our thermochemical
data we can do six point zero seven
moles times negative five thousand 461
kilojoules that are released for every
mole of iso-octane and we get negative
three point three one times ten to the
four kilojoules that is how much energy is associated with the combustion of one liter of isooctane.